Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Read, Franklin. Cape François
    His reasons for deciding to follow the sea; has been unfortunate up to this time but is now in a fair way to succeed; has just come up from Jamaica on parole but expects to be exchanged in a day or two; shall then return home where he has a good berth in a vessel bound for Europe; hopes Franklin will forgive him for not writing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, James. Bordeaux
    Recommending Mr. Anthony Lynch for the position of American Agent at the above prot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Puy, Bishop of. Puy
    Has established, in his diocese of Languedoc, various manufactories in order to help the poor by giving them work; begs Frankliln to honor them with his orders for the United States. Reminds Franklin of their meeting in 1778 at the chateau of M. Bertin, the Minister.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    The bearers of this are Whipple Crow and Benjamin Slocum, Americans taken on board the "Polly" and carried to Bristol; having made their escape, they arrived in France destitute of everything; drew on Franklin for money to take them to Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Wyld, Henry. Hatherlow
    Sorry to hear that Franklin's authority to grant their request has been recalled; desires that they be given the earliest opportunity to emigrate as they wish to be the first persons to arrive in the capacity of manufacturers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    The bearers are John Kemp and Alex Findats, Americans, Captain and Lieutenant on board the "Greyhound"; their capture, imprisonment in England and subsequent escape; their arrival in France destitute; drew on Franklin for money to take them to Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Enclosed letter to be forwarded to Boston; leaves soon for Chatillon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Faucon, ------. Riou
    Writes for news of his son Julien; gives account of his movements from the time he entered the French navy up to the year 1780, when he ceased to hear from him; rumor that he is living in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Tezenad, ------. Passy
    Offering to send to Franklin a musket, pair of pistols, rifle and powderhorn, all of exquisite workmanship; thinks they would be a worthy present for General Washington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. St Germain
    Thanking Franklin for the return of his papers; feels sure that he has solid reasons for declining the execution of the plan; reasons why he will not fulfill Franklin's suggestion to render it successful elsewhere. His two girls go to town that day, one to stay with Mme. de la Marck, the other to visit Mme. Helvétius.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Clegg, Edmund
    Sorry that Franklin's interest in Mr. Wyld's undertaking was dampened by the delay in the payment of the bill upon himself; distress and confusion caused by Franklin's letter; certain of their friends have gone too far to retreat now. His plans for establishing a silk manufactory in America; success he has made of it in the past. If the country can yield a sufficient quantity of raw silk they can make it independent of Europe for those goods. If it cannot, then hopes that the Italian and East India markets may be opened in the meantime. For more than twenty years has set his heart on emigrating to America. If they do not go this season he wishes to go with his two sons as soon as possible. He thinks all the real liberty now or hereafter enjoyed in this island may be attributed to the noble heroes of North America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Reproaches him for not having answered any of his letters; particularly anxious to have his opinion upon the heat conducting quality of different metals; on this account, has retarded one year the publication of the book which he now sends. Attack made on his work by Dr. Priestley; convinced he can prove him wrong in his whole theory about the manner in which vegetables are subservient to the animal creation. Begs for news of Mr. Samuel Wharton who has large sums of his money to invest in trade.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Murray, Mlle. Gand
    Informing him of the loss of her friend, Mme. Battier; has been obliged to take entire charge of her affairs; begs permission to send him a small box containing her friend's portrait, surrounded with diamonds, and a gold chain, which she wore up to her death; desires this box delivered to her friend's father, Mr. [Thomas] Ivers [at Boston].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 25; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Sends the required permission for the books to be delivered at Rochefort without a visit from the Syndics.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Putnam, Benjamin. Portsmouth, Va
    His vessels depending on the Admiralty of France; desires some information on the subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Stewart, Mary. London
    Begs for assistance; is in great pecuniary distress owing to an expensive law-suit and a long illness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Trouillot, -----. Lyon
    Desires to go to America; begs Franklin to aid him with advice and recommendations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Estaing, Charles-Henri, comte d'.
    Sends back the list to Franklin; the articles marked with a cross are the ones he desires.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Forster, Johann Reinhold. Halle
    Introducing Mr. Loder, First Physician to the Duke of Saxe-Weimar, and one of the first German anatornists. Congratulates him on the prospect of America's independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbançon, Augustin-Jean-Louis-Antoine du Prat, comte de. Varennes
    Thanking him for his present of rare seeds.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 28; A.L.S. 2p.; West, Benjamin. London
    Greatly pleased with a bust of Franklin he has just procured. His eldest son, now in his sixteenth year, has greatly improved in painting; while his thirteen-year-old boy shows great facility in learning. Refers Franklin to Mr. Whitefoord as regards his own situation.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 20.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782 April 28]; L.S. 2p.; Barons, Anthony and A. Cummings
    Have been long held prisoners in England. Beg for help to return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782] April 29; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Alexander, Miss Bethia.
    Asking Franklin to carry a packet into Paris for her father; unless he takes it in his own carriage, it would be stopped at the city gate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 29; A.D. 2p.; Ollivier, ----- (notaire royale) and Le Guével, Th. Passy
    Concerning a bill of exchange payable to Benjamin Franklin and drawn on Jonathan Nesbitt; the latter's refusal to accept it; account of the proceedings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Arnold, Freegift. L'Orient
    Account of his adventures as an officer in the service of Congress; his long imprisonment and final escape; has not a farthing to his name and owes Mr. Moylan for his subsistence; desires his share of the prizemoney due him from the "Alliance," or a small advance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 April 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Intention of Mr. James Moore of Scotland to enter into the American trade in France; his wish to take the oath of allegiance to the United States; sends one signed before witnesses. Begs for an answer about the American prisoners still boarding at his expense.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Richard, --------. Paris
    The Professor of rhetoric in his College offered a prize for the best French translation of the famous Latin verse— "Eripuit coelo fulmen, sceptrumque tyrannis"; quotes his own translation which carried off the palm.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Ruston, Thomas. Exeter
    Presumes Franklin forwarded the scheme of a bank to Mr. Morris, as he has since seen a Resolve of Congress to give Mr. Morris ample powers to carry such a scheme into execution. In Case of peace or truce, suggests that America institute a loan in England; discusses the advantages of such a step; its probable popularity in England; the question of security.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Ruston, Thomas. Exeter
    Introducing Major Van Braam, a native of Holland, who quitted the English army two years before, after thirty years' service; his intention to remove to France with his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Etienne Caÿrol and Cie. Paris
    Establishment at Amsterdam of an emporium for goods from their manufactory of Gobelins; have appointed Paul Charlé their Agent for whom they beg a recommendation to Mr. Adams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 5; Extract from L. 3p.; Cooper, Dr Samuel. Boston
    Letters received in this State and at Philadelphia, stating that France was at the bottom against America obtaining the fishery and territory in that great extent in which both are secured to America by the treaty; that the American Minister did not oppose this design, and that it was entirely owing to the firmness, sagacity and disinterestedness of Mr.Adams and Mr. Jay, that America obtained those important advantages. States that these letters are said to come from Mr. Adams, States that Mr. Adams wrote to Congress resigning his employments in Europe but intimated in a subsequent letter his readiness to continue them should he be appointed Minister to the Court of London.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, X, 6; Bigelow, VIII, 340).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Hotel de Vauban
    Introducing M. de la Grainehais who desires information relative to a deed of lands in Pennsylvania.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Allcock, William. Amiens
    His services in the American army since 1777; his capture by the English; his arrival in France and his destitute condition; desires assistance; names of five other prisoners who arrived with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Bassi, Anton-Benedetto. Paris
    Franklin's admission to the membership of the Academy of Padua shows how much he is esteemed in Italy; desires subscription to his "Complete Collection of the Most Beautiful Selections from Italian Poetry."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, Thomas. Amiens
    Mistake made by M. Leleu; these unhappy Americans are able to prove that they do not come from English prisons; hopes Franklin will give them the desired assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Leleu, N., l'aîné
    Explaining the mistake be made in saying six Americans had arrived from English prisons; true account of their capture and arrival in France; can vouch for their not being English spies in disguise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 7; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Paris
    Enclosing fourteen bills which he begs Franklin to accept and return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Etienne Caÿrol and Cie. Paris
    Their request for a letter of recommendation to Mr. Adams on behalf of Mr. Paul Charlé.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Embser, Johann Valentin
    In accordance with his orders, sends him the twenty-six volumes of the Collections of Ancient Roman Authors and one volume of the Greek.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Hopes the exchange of prisoners will take place the following week. The letters to go to Congress by the cartel vessels must be forwarded at once. Presented Franklin's acknowledgments to the "noble personage" for his kindness and attention to Americans. Pleasing prospect of peace. Messages from Drs. Priestley and Price, and Messrs. Jones and Paradise. Money due him for disbursements to prisoners. Desires Franklin to send a special messenger at his expense with earliest news of whether there will or will not be a Congress to treat on terms of pacification.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Clegg, Edmund
    Their friends have gone too far to retreat; begs Franklin to do the most he can towards rendering their passage over safe. His views on the establishment of a silk manufactory in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 10; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Baucher, Denis
    An officer on board the "Bon Homme Richard," Commodore Paul Jones; in the engagement with the "Serapis," was so seriously wounded that he has become a hopeless invalid; begs for his share of the prizemoney to alleviate the situation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Clegg, Edmund
    Acknowledging the pass and letters of recommendation. Misunderstood the conference between Franklin and Mr. Wyld; thinks the latter was perhaps too sanguine. His intention of persuading his friends in the country, if possible, to delay their departure till peace is established; if they are resolved to go, will risk everything to go with them. Account of his interview with Mr. [Henry] Laurens who, owing to the delicacy of his situation, could not comply with his request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 12; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Percival, Dr. Thomas. Manchester
    Requesting Dr. Franklin's acceptance of the enclosed volumes as memorials of his cordial esteem and respect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Rouaix, Prof. Toulouse
    Is greatly flattered that Franklin will accept the dedication of his general thesis on philosophy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782.] May 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Dufaux, Morel. Paris
    Important services rendered by him to the American cause; hopes Franklin will permit an introduction by his friend, M. Grand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Pownall, Thomas. Richmond
    Sending him an account of the sale of his "Topographical Description of America," in order that the poor widow Barry may receive her just dues. Hoped to have been legally authorized to communicate with Franklin on the subject of peace. Sees he will never be employed in Europe on account of the objection to him of one person.
    Printed, in part, in Hale's Franklin in France II, 22.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Cutler, B.C. Paris
    Concerning the miniature of the late Mrs. Battier which Miss Murray, of Ghent, sent to Franklin's care; desires him to forward it to Mr. Thomas Ivers at Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Report of America having declared war against Portugal; if this is true, would like a commission for the "Spry" to cruize against the Portugese. News of a bloody engagement between the Comte de Grasse and Mr. Rodney; advantage doubtful. Message from Capt. Jon. Coffin of Nantucket.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Harvey, Reuben. Cork
    Desire of about one hundred poor tradesmen and husbandmen to settle in America; having no money to pay their passage, they propose to indent as servants for a certain term; the owner of the ship unwilling to accept them in this manner without being sure of the approval of Congress; can assure him that there is not a convict or felon amongst them.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. Contrasting the condition of the poor in America with those in other lands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 July 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Vidal, -----, et al. L'Orient
    Desiring some information about a young man whose mother is distracted with grief over his reported death in York, Virginia; begging Franklin to ascertain the truth of this rumor and any other details obtainable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Laurens, Henry. Ostend
    Sending certain letters and apologizing for their detention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 28; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution instructing the Minister at the Court of Versailles to take immediate measures for liquidating the accounts between the United States and that Court and report a state thereof to Congress; also appointing a Commissioner to liquidate and settle the accounts of all the servants of the United States who have been entrusted with the expenditure of public moneys in Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 21; L.S. 2p.; Coppens, -----, fils. Dunkirk
    Is about to send Capt. John Moultson, an American, on a new cruize with the schooner "Sophia"; hearing that war was declared by the United States against Portugal, writes for a commission of war for the Captain so that he may cruize under American colors against the enemies of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 22; L.S. 1p.; J.F. Frin and Co. Paris
    Enclosing a bill of exchange for acceptance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning M. de Castries's request for a ship to be freighted at Nantes for the service of the United States; must have further orders. Urges some action as regards the American prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Lacepède, Bernard-Germain-Etienne de La Ville-sur-Illon, comte de. Paris
    His regret at leaving Paris without having paid his respects to Franklin; his first volume on physics about to appear.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Gerbier, ------. Francouville
    Requesting a passport to be issued to his cousin at Nantes for the latter's vessel "Nostra Signora."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782. Circa May 24.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gerbier and Cie. Nantes
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to give them a letter of protection for their vessel "Nostra Signora" bound from Nantes to San Domingo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d'Auberteuil, Michel-René
    Hopes that the little monument he has wished to erect to the memory of Miss MacRea will prove acceptable to her friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Saussine, Pierre. Nimes
    M. Boudon, an orphan, left to the care of a tutor; enticed away from this protector by relatives who desired his small fortune; persuaded by them to go to America; his adventures at St. Eustatius where he lost everything; his arrival in Philadelphia; unless Mr. Wharton has protected him, his tutor and friends fear the worse; begs Dr. Franklin to ascertain his whereabouts and hasten his return.
    (In French. See XXV, 103.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Gerbier, ------
    Thanking him for listening to his relative's request [for a passport for the "Nostra Signora"].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Circa June 1; N.S. de Séqueville. 1p.; The Secretary to the King
    Postponing the King's reception of the Ambassadors and Foreign Ministers to the 8th of June, 1782.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Bassée, ----- de la. Boulogne
    His son desires to enter the American service; begs Franklin to procure him the position of officer in the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Coxe, Tench. Philadelphia
    Loss of certain bills of exchange; begs Franklin to refuse them if presented.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Recommends that the terms of peace should be marked by generous language and humane measures; is sure that no liberality will meet with a repulse. He may hear of Mr. [Henry] Lauren's strange behavior from Mr. Oswald. Has given orders for shipping £6000 in goods to America; increase of emigration there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Acknowledging receipt of £200; gratitude of the prisoners for the kindness shown them. Departure of the three hundred prisoners from Portsmouth; rumors of their being riotous and ungovernable unfounded. There will be upwards of seven hundred prisoners in Plymouth including those arrived from Kinsale. Convinced that certain persons in power mean to walk fairly and uprightly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Introducing his friend Mr. Henry Mitchell of Boston just arrived on the ship "Alexander" from Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 8; L.S. 2p.; von Steuben, W. A. Cüstrin
    Congratulates Dr. Franklin on his success in the American cause. Encloses a letter to his son, the General, with the request to forward. Complains that his son has not answered for a year his letters. Would like to hear of him before he dies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, Joseph. Cape Saint Nicholas, Haiti
    Concerning a prize captured by him in his brig, "Lady Grune", commissioned by Congress; the sloop was judged and condemned as a good prize to the captors; begs Franklin, on receipt of the enclosed papers (1p.), to order the money paid him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Introducing Mr. Foy who intends staying near Paris in order to perfect himself in the French Language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Ridley, Matthew. Amsterdam
    Account received of M. de la Luzerne's house in Philadelphia having been struck by lightning; the accident imputed to the want of Dr. Franklin's lightning-rods. General Knox and Mr.Gouverneur Morris appointed by Gen. Washington to negotiate an exchange of prisoners. Mr. Gadsden elected Governor of South Carolina by declined serving; British property in that State confiscated; the reason given. Account of the action on the Delaware between the American vessel "Hyder Ally" and the British "General Monk", sloop of war, which ended in the latter's being taken. Just recovering from an attack of epidemic influenza.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 10; L.S. 3p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a copy of XXIV, 146 (see p. 463); Baron d' Arendt had the misfortune to be captured and carried into New York; being released on parole he obtained the above copy, having lost the original.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Arrival of the "Don Galvez" from Salem, which she left December 1st.; at that time, M. de. Vandreuil with the fleet remained at Boston and did not expect to sail untill the end of the month. Fresh cruelties committed by the Indians on the back settlements near Sunbury.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Bouvinghausen, Maj. Gen. ----- de
    Begs him to forward the enclosed letter for Baron de Steuben at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Rotterdam
    Begging him not to accept certain bills drawn on them by their friends Curson and Gouverneur, at St. Eustatius, and the cause; concerning certain bills of Congress in their possession; desire advice how to procure their payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan